Finding Aid for Aliya Hassen Papers, 1910-1991
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Aliya Hassen Papers 1910-1991
Hassen, Aliya, 1910-1990.
9280 Aa 2; UAm
Arab-American community leader in the Dearborn-Detroit area of Michigan. Articles, manuscripts and poems on Islamic topics; topical files, 1948-1991, relating to Arab community affairs, including files concerning the Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services, 1986-1991 and the Federation of Islamic Associations of the U.S. and Canada; also correspondence and articles of Malcolm X; and photographs.
1.5 linear feet
1 oversize folders
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received from Ismail Ahmed, the Executive Director of ACCESS, in November 1991. (Donor No. 7938 )
The collection is open to research.
Seen by many as the "mother" of the Dearborn-Detroit Arab community, Aliya Ogdie-Hassen was born in South Dakota on April 30, 1910, the daughter of immigrant homesteaders from Lebanon. At the age of 14, Hassen entered into a prearranged marriage, which eventually ended in divorce sixteen years later. In 1925, Hassen left South Dakota to live with cousins in Detroit.
In the early 1950s, Hassen moved to New York City. It was there that she earned her private investigator's license. Serving in a number of retail security positions, Hassen also served as the Civil Defense Director of Brooklyn's 82nd Precinct.
During her years in New York, Aliya Ogdie-Hassen became actively involved in a number of Islamic organizations that worked towards social change in both the United States and the Arab world. This included organizing the Egyptian Arab American Seaman's Society. Hassen also acted as a liaison between the Federation of Islamic Associations of the United States and Canada and the U.S. Black Muslim movement known as the Nation of Islam. It was during this period that Hassen formed a lasting friendship with Malcolm X. Her friendship and correspondence with Malcolm X grew out of her work to unite Islamic organizations and to spread the message of an egalitarian Islam. Her work led her to the Middle East where she made a pilgrimage to Mecca and developed friendships with Arab leaders.
In 1972, Aliya Ogdie-Hassen moved back to Detroit and assisted in the development of the newly formed Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services (ACCESS). She organized English classes and helped with food, housing and translations for hundreds of new immigrants of Arab descent. Serving as ACCESS director for nine years, Hassen helped transform the organization from a storefront operation into a full-fledged social services agency that offered medical, legal, educational, and other services to thousands of Arab families on an annual basis. For her work in the organization, Hassen received dozens of awards and citations which included the prestigious national Jefferson Award. After stepping down as director in 1982, Aliya Ogdie-Hassen continued to serve on the board and executive committee of ACCESS until her death in May 1990.
The Aliya Ogdie-Hassen Papers are divided into Articles, Manuscripts and Poems, Topical Files, Photographs, and Sound Recordings.
Subjects:
Arab Americans--Michigan.; Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services.; Federation of Islamic Associations in the U.S.A. & Canada.; Hassen, Aliya, 1910-1990.; Islam.; X, Malcolm, 1925-1965.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Arab Americans--Michigan.; Hassen, Aliya, 1910-1990.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.; Sound recordings.
- Articles, Manuscripts, and Poems 1923-1959
  Articles, Manuscripts and Poems contain both published and unpublished material written and collected by Aliya Ogdie-Hassen during her lifetime. Included in this series are articles written for the Islamic Information Series. These articles were later published in Muslim Life the journal of the Federation of Islamic Associations in the U.S. and Canada. Also included are several manuscripts that contain various Islamic children's stories which Hassen collected throughout the Arab world. Another manuscript contains various Arabic and Islamic cooking recipes that she had likewise collected during her travels. Lastly, the series contains a single hardbound volume of poetry that was written by Aliya Ogdie-Hassen between 1923 and 1940. There is also a folder of miscellaneous poems written both by Aliya and her only daughter, Amelia Hussein.
  - Islamic Information Series Articles undated (Box 1)
  - Manuscripts
    - The Crescent and the Cross undated (Box 1)
    - Good Eating With Muslims Around the World undated (Box 1)
    - The 101 Questions Most Frequently Asked of Muslims 1959 (Box 1)
    - Religious Stories for Young Muslims undated (Box 1)
    - Wives of the Prophet Muhammad 1959 (Box 1)
  - Poems
    - 1923-1940, 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous Poetry undated (Box 1)
- Topical Files 1948-1991
  Topical Files contains materials documenting Aliya Ogdie-Hassen's life and work in both New York City and Detroit. Arranged alphabetically, this series includes family and miscellaneous correspondence, materials relating to her civil defense and private security work in New York, materials relating to her involvement in Muslim social organizations, which includes the Islamic Center and the Egyptian Arab American Seaman's Society, and materials relating to both her and her grandson's work in ACCESS.
  - Arab Community Center for Economic and Social Services (ACCESS)
    - Articles, Correspondence, and Miscellaneous 1986-1991 (Box 1)
    - Cultural Museum 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - Hate Mail 1988 (Box 1)
  - Biographical Material 1983-1990 (Box 1)
  - Civil Defense Material 1952-1968 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence
    - Family 1948-1973 (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Egyptian Arab American Seaman's Society 1959 (Box 1)
  - Federation of Islamic Associations of the U.S. and Canada
    - Egyptian Trip 1961 (Box 1)
    - F.I.A. Journals 1965 (Box 1)
    - Muslim Star 1973 (Box 1)
  - The Islamic Center 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - Islamic Funeral Rites and Shrouding Instructions (Box 1)
  - Islamic Sorority-Constitution (Box 1)
  - Malcolm X (Articles and Correspondence) 1959-1965 (Box 1)
  - Marble Collegiate Church 1968 (Box 1)
  - Mecca Trip Journal December 1975 (Box 1)
  - Michigan Awards and Letters 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - Palestine Arab Delegation 1963 (Box 1)
  - Speech on Arab Immigration (Box 1)
  - Syrian Junior League 1948 (Box 1)
- Photographs
  Photographs consists of five folders and one outsize folder. Arranged alphabetically, the series contains numerous snapshots of Aliya Ogdie-Hassen and her family members, vacation and travel photos from both London and Mecca, and miscellaneous photos which are mostly undated.
  - Family Photographs, 3 folders; 1 oversize folders (Box 2)
  - Group and Miscellaneous Photographs (Box 2)
  - Vacation and Travel Photographs (Box 2)
- Sound Recordings, 1978-1982
  Sound Recordings consists of seven audiocassette tapes. The topics of these tapes include Arab immigration and contribution to culture, family and childhood stories narrated by Aliya Ogdie-Hassen, a speech given to the Kiwanis Club, and information on the Southend Dearborn Health and Social Services.
  - Arab Immigration and Contributions to Culture 1978, 2 tapes (Box 2)
  - Childhood and Family Stories 1979 (Box 2)
  - Kiwanis Speech 1982 (Box 2)
  - Music from Qatar undated (Box 2)
  - Southend Dearborn Health and Social Services 1978 (Box 2)
  - Wives of the Prophet Muhammad undated (Box 2)